<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Productivity | Michel P. Macedo]]></title>
  <link href="http://michelpm.com/categories/productivity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://michelpm.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-12T06:45:16-03:00</updated>
  <id>http://michelpm.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Michel Pavan Macedo]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[michelpm@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lines of Code and Kilos of Cake]]></title>
    <link href="http://michelpm.com/2014/12/18/lines-of-code-and-kilos-of-cake/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-18T00:00:00-02:00</updated>
    <id>http://michelpm.com/2014/12/18/lines-of-code-and-kilos-of-cake</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I love statistics, so I keep track of lots of stuff and make statistics about it later. I knew approximately how many hours I had spent in a pet project, so I decided to calculate how many lines, words and characters I had written per hour. Linux has tools that get that data for me.</p>

<pre><code>&gt; cat public/index.html public/js/indice.js carga/eleitos/presidentes.txt carga/importa_eleitos.rb carga/gera_json.rb carga/analisa_partidos.rb publish_to_github.sh carga/resultados_no_tse.md dev.md config.ru Gemfile | wc
   1997    5106   61796
</code></pre>

<p>There is a problem with that, though. Actually, a few. I know nothing about pastry, but let&rsquo;s pretend I am baker and I am measuring my productivity in kilograms of cake per hour (more relatable to people who know little about software development like clients and managers).</p>

<h2>Kilos of Taste</h2>

<p>I don&rsquo;t really need to say this, but I will anyway. There is a pretty obvious difference between baking tasty edible cake and lots of cake. I can produce a ton of mudpie and it will be worth less than 100 grams of Mississipi Mud Pie.</p>

<h2>Kilos of Frosting Spatulas</h2>

<p>Often I will have to build a specific tool for my cake. When measuring I&rsquo;ll tell myself I spent so many hours because I had to build a tool for that. Then I realize that the tool shares the concept of mass with cakes, so for stastical purposes I add 100 grams of tools to the total mass of things I created.</p>

<h2>Kilos of Drawings</h2>

<p>I spend hours working in a carefully elaborated frosting. I weigh the cake again and I add 100 grams to the total mass.</p>

<h2>Kilos of Recipes</h2>

<p>There is a difference between following the same recipe a thousand times and building a different or personalized cake every time. It may even require researching for recipes and learning how to do some different kind of pastry or frosting. None of this weighs anything.</p>

<h2>Weightless Tons of Rejects</h2>

<p>It may require <strong>a lot</strong> of failed tests that will not be added to the total mass, but they will still cost and be paid by the client. You may still consciously leave this out, but you are assuming rejects mean incompentence and it may not always be the case. There is a difference between the concepts of productivity with and without this.</p>

<h2>Kilos of Work</h2>

<p>If you are only counting kilograms of mass produced you are either assuming all work of a productive baker generates more mass, that the work that do not produce mass is negligible or that the amount work that do not produce mass has a high correlation to the mass produced. I never worked in a confectionery, but in software development any of those assumptions is naïve to say the least.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
